Guide to the Jock Elliott Papers, 1945-2005 and undated, bulk 1961-1982 RL.00359
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jock Elliott papers
1945-2005 and undated, bulk 1961-1982
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Elliott, Jock
RL.00359
12.6 Linear Feet
John Jock Elliott was an executive with Ogilvy & Mather (O&M) during 1960-1982, including tenure as Chairman of O&M U.S. and O&M International. In addition, Elliott was an author, collector and philanthropist. The Jock Elliott Papers cover the years 1945-2005, with the bulk of materials dating from 1961-1982, the period during which Elliott served as an executive with Ogilvy & Mather (O&M) advertising agency. The collection primarily consists of correspondence, corporate annual reports, programs, speeches and photographs related to company meetings and events. The collection also includes videocassettes and memorabilia commemorating meetings and special events; materials relating to Eleanor Elliott and David Ogilvy; information on affirmative action hiring programs; as well as some speeches and correspondence from the period 1945-1959 when Elliott worked for the Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborn (BBDO) advertising agency. Companies represented in the collection include Shell Oil, Du Pont Men's Wear and Trans World Airlines (TWA).
9450 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original videotapes are closed to research until use copies can be made. Contact Research Services for more information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jock Elliott Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts in 2005-2007. A portion of accession 2007-0067, the Eleanor Elliott Papers, which deals with Jock Elliott's professional life, was removed and interfiled with the present collection.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1921 Born John Elliott, New York, N.Y.
1928-1934 Attended the Browing School, New York, N.Y.
1938 Attended the St. Paul's School, Concord, N.H.
1942 Received A.B. from Harvard College
1942 Joined the U.S. Marine Corps
1945 Joined BBDO as copywriter
1946 Married Eleanor Thomas
1950-1953 Served as television advisor to Republican Party
1956 Became BBDO Vice President
1958 Became BBDO Management Supervisor
1960 Joined O&M as Senior Vice President-Director
1965 Chairman of O&M U.S.
1975 Chairman of O&M International
1974-1975 Chairman of American Association of Advertising Agencies
1982 Retired from O&M
1983 Inducted into Advertising Hall of Fame
1999 Published A Ha! Christmas
2001 Published Inventing Christmas, How Our Holiday Came to Be
2005 Died, Mt. Kisko, N.Y.
John "Jock" Elliott grew up in New York City, and attended the Browning School on the Upper East Side of Manhattan, St. Paul's School in Concord, New Hampshire, and eventually Harvard College. In 1942, he joined the U.S. Marine Corps, and spent most of World War II as a major on the battleship Pennsylvania. After being discharged in 1945, he began working for the Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborn (BBDO) advertising agency as a copywriter. He soon switched to management and within a few years, he became the company's youngest director. During his 15 year tenure with BBDO, he also served as account man for the Republican Party's Eisenhower-Nixon team.
Elliott joined Ogilvy & Mather (O&M) in 1960 as Senior Vice President-Director and was soon placed in charge of acquiring the Shell Oil account, O&M's largest account at the time. In 1965, David Ogilvy appointed Elliott the chairman of O&M U.S., and in 1975 as chairman of O&M International. Under Elliott's leadership, O&M's domestic billings increased from $84 million to $252 million, and international billings from $659 million to $2.03 billion. He was responsible for acquiring such clients as IBM and American Express, and for attempting to acquire the J. Walter Thompson agency in 1979, a plan that did not materialize. In 1983 he was inducted into the Advertising Hall of Fame.
Elliott also served as Chairman of the American Association of Advertising Agencies (AAAA); Chairman of the American Advertising Federation's Hall of Fame Committee; Director of the New York City Park Association; Vice President and Trustee of the Museum of the City of New York; Trustee of the Wildlife Conservation Society and of the Browning School; and Life Trustee of Channel Thirteen. He also served on President Reagan's Advisory Board on Private Sector Initiatives, and was a member of the Racquet and Tennis Club, the Piping Rock Club and New York's Harvard Club. Outside of advertising, Elliott was known for his sizeable collection of Christmas books, which included more than 3,000 first editions, and which resulted in publication of two volumes: A Ha! Christmas, An Exhibition of Jock Elliott's Christmas Books (1999) and Inventing Christmas, How Our Holiday Came to Be (2001). He died in 2005.
Collection Overview
The Jock Elliott Papers cover the years 1945-2005, with the bulk of materials dating from 1961-1982, the period during which Elliott served as an executive with Ogilvy & Mather (O&M) advertising agency. The collection primarily consists of correspondence, corporate annual reports, programs, speeches and photographs related to company meetings and events. The collection also includes videocassettes and memorabilia commemorating meetings and special events; materials relating to Eleanor Elliott and David Ogilvy; information on affirmative action hiring programs; as well as some speeches and correspondence from the period 1945-1959 when Elliott worked for the Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborn (BBDO) advertising agency. Companies represented in the collection include Shell Oil, Du Pont Men's Wear and Trans World Airlines (TWA).
Note for clarification: Ogilvy & Mather (O&M) was co-founded by David Ogilvy in 1948. Originally called Hewitt, Ogilvy, Benson, and Mather (OBM), in 1953 the company name was shortened to Ogilvy & Mather (O&M). Both entities are present in this collection.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eleven series: Account Books; Clippings; Correspondence; Meetings; Memorabilia; Printed Material; Reports; Stocks; Writings and Speeches; Audiovisual Materials; and Oversize Materials. Account Books include small appointment books maintained by Jock Elliott. Clippings consist of newspaper and magazine clippings related to management changes at O&M, advertising trends, overseas travels of Jock and Eleanor Elliott, feature stories on the Elliotts and David Ogilvy, and articles on advertising in which Jock Elliott was quoted. Correspondence includes letters and memoranda between Jock Elliott and O&M employees and affiliates, general memoranda to O&M staff, and congratulatory letters to Elliott on occasions of his career promotions. Meetings consist of correspondence, itineraries and flyers related to various O&M and AAAA meetings. Memorabilia include awards, photographs of business and personal travels, and small mementos of celebratory events. Printed Material include programs, selected issues of advertising journals and magazines, and books related to O&M. Reports include prepared reports on hiring statistics in advertising agencies, proposals for potential advertising campaigns, annual reports and market research reports. Stocks include correspondence and shareholders reports related to O&M stocks and mergers. Audiovisual Materials consist of videotapes documenting the careers of Jock and Eleanor Elliott, and of particular meetings and events of O&M or the Advertising Hall of Fame. Writings and Speeches primarily consist of typescripts of Jock Elliott's speeches given at company and AAAA meetings, general advertising events, and events of colleges, universities and clubs. Also includes drafts and published versions of Elliott's poems and articles. Oversize Materials consist of large format items removed from other series, and include a commemorative binder prepared for Elliott's sixtieth birthday, posters, as well as large magazine issues and clippings.
Many of the materials arrived loose and unfoldered. These items were grouped first by type of material, then by subject title, and finally by date, where possible. Items that arrived in report covers, binders and clear plastic sleeves were removed and foldered, with original titles maintained. Photographs that arrived in albums were removed and placed in mylar sleeves, grouped by album subject with original titles maintained. Photographs that arrived paperclipped together according to theme were similarly placed in sleeves, and organized by original title.
Related Material
Materials pertaining to the Ogilvy & Mather agency may be found in the William E. Phillips Papers, Anthony Weir Papers, Edgar Hatcher Papers, the Robert S. Smith Papers, the David B. McCall Papers, the J. Walter Thompson Company Advertising Vertical Files, and the American Association of Advertising Agencies Records. Materials pertaining to Elliott's personal life and philanthropic activities may also be found in the Eleanor Elliott Papers.
Advertising agencies -- United States -- Management; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising executives -- United States; Affirmative action programs -- United States -- Management; Marketing research -- United States; Corporation reports; Appointment books; Speeches; Photographs; Clippings (information artifacts); Memorabilia; Videocassettes; Ogilvy, David, 1911-1999; Ogilvy & Mather; Trans World Airlines; Shell Oil Company; Elliott, Eleanor; Elliott, Jock; Elliott, Jock; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; American Association of Advertising Agencies; Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborn, Inc.
- Appointment Books, 1961-2004, 3 Boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains Jock Elliott's appointment books from the years 1961-2004. Arranged chronologically with the exception of the book for 1978, which is located in Box 3.
  - 1961-1976, 16 books (Box 1)
  - 1977-2004, 27 books (Box 2)
  - 1978 (Box 3)
- Clippings, 1960-2005 and undated, 1 Box
  Contains news and magazine clippings related to Jock Elliott's and David Ogilvy's careers; administrative changes at O&M; Elliott's overseas travels as Chair of O&M international; and advertising trends. Also includes clippings related to the employment of minorities and women in advertising; and related to the publication of Elliott's two Christmas books. Original folder titles were retained, where applicable. Where no arrangement was provided, items were arranged roughly by subject. Large-format items have been removed to Oversize Materials and noted in the container list.
  - [Advertising Age, 1961-2002: Removed to Oversize Materials, Box 22] (Box 3)
  - [Argentina visit, 1986-1987: Removed to Oversize Materials, Box 22] (Box 3)
  - Asia trips, 1975-1980 (Box 3)
  - Australia trip, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Christmas books publicity, 1999, 2002 (Some items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 22) (Box 3)
  - [Confessions of a Magazine Reader, 1965: Removed to Oversize Folder 1] (Box 3)
  - Diversity in hiring, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Elliott features, 1973-2003 (Box 3)
  - Ogilvy & Mather
    - General, 1964-2005 (Box 3)
    - Obituaries, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Sale, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Tear sheets, undated (Box 3)
  - Who Runs America, U.S. News & World Report, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous magazine clippings, 1960-2004 (Some items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 22) (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1947-1996 and undated, 7 Boxes
  Contains primarily business related correspondence between Jock Elliott and O&M employees and affiliates, with the bulk of material dating between 1965 and 1982. Includes memoranda relating to meetings of advertisers in the U.S. and abroad; O&M overseas branches; particular accounts; the advisability of cigarette advertising campaigns; as well as correspondence regarding Elliott's speeches; and several folders of correspondence between Elliott and David Ogilvy. Also includes memoranda regarding O&M Securities Exchange Commission transgressions; and Elliott's correspondence during his years spent at BBDO. Several folders contain carbon copies of Elliott's correspondence files between the years 1967 and 1978. Also includes correspondence relating to the TWA Airlines account. Original folder titles were maintained and folders were arranged alphabetically.
  - General, 1965-1979 (Box 3)
  - AAAA annual meeting, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Acquisition of Scali McCabe Sloves, 1976 (Box 4)
  - American Association of Advertising Agencies, 1978 (Box 4)
  - BBDO, 1947-1950 (Box 4)
  - Caples, John, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Cigarette advertising, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Colossus merger, 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - Congratulatory, 1965-1966, 1-3 of 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Congratulatory (continued), 1965-1966, 4-7 of 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Elliott's 75th birthday, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Fire advertisement, 1969 (Some items removed to Oversize Folder 2) (Box 5)
  - Hall of Fame congratulations, 1980-1984 (Box 5)
  - International Management Meeting, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Kershaw, Andrew, O&M Canada President
    - General, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Condolences and service arrangements, 1978 (Box 5)
  - London talk, 1977-1978 (Some items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 22) (Box 5)
  - London and Australia visits, 1969 (Box 5)
  - MBA Communications, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Moss, Frank (Senator), 1974 (Box 6)
  - National Press Club of Australia, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Ogilvy, David, 1965-1980, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - O'Hara, Sir Robert, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Overseas branches (Box 7)
    - China, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Germany, 1979-1981 (Box 7)
    - Italy, 1979-1982 (Box 7)
    - Japan, 1979-1982 (Box 7)
    - London, 1979-1981 (Box 7)
  - Post-Keyes-Gardner account, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Rereads, 1967-1978, 1-3 of 14 folders (Box 7)
  - Rereads (continued), 1967-1978, 4-13 of 14 folders (Box 8)
  - Rereads (continued), 1967-1978, 14 of 14 folders (Box 9)
  - Security Exchange Commission Transgressions, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Speech-related correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 9)
  - Staff memoranda, 1965-1984 (Box 9)
  - Succession, 1978-1979 (Box 9)
  - Sudler & Hennessey acquisitions and merger, 1971-1972 (Box 9)
  - TWA Airlines, 1968-1972 (Box 9)
  - Travel itineraries, 1977 and undated (Box 9)
  - Wunderman, Ricotta and Kline, 1964-1966 (Box 9)
- Meetings, 1968-1994 and undated, 2 Boxes
  Contains correspondence, memoranda and flyers relating to O&M staff meetings; the Advertising Hall of Fame luncheon; and events of the AAAA. Original folder titles were maintained and arranged alphabetically. Meeting programs were moved into the Printed Materials series, and speeches were moved into the Writings and Speeches series. Miscellaneous unfoldered photographs of meetings were placed in this series.
  - AAAA annual meeting, 1978 (Box 10)
  - AAAA Puerto Rico, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Advertising Educational Foundation Board of Directors meeting photograph, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Board Meeting photographs, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Hall of Fame luncheon, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Heads of Offices Meeting, 1973 (Box 10)
  - International Management Meeting, 1976 (Box 10)
  - International Management Meeting, 1979 (Box 11)
  - Merrill Lynch marketing policy meetings, 1968-1978 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous meeting photographs, 1977-1884 (Box 11)
- Memorabilia, 1965-2003, 2 Boxes
  Contains awards, certificates and ephemera relating to Elliott's major life events while employed at O&M, including birthday and retirement celebrations. Also includes photographs of O&M employees and affiliates in the U.S. and abroad; of Elliott's business and personal travels; and a photograph and letter from Ronald Reagan regarding the President's Citation Program for Private Sector Initiatives. Framed items were removed and placed in folders. In the case of travel memorabilia, which arrived paperclipped together with a group label, label titles were maintained. Photographs arriving in albums were removed and placed in album specific folders. Scrapbook prepared for Elliott in celebration of his sixtieth birthday was placed in a separate oversize box. Unfoldered items were placed in folders of miscellaneous photographs or ephemera. Large-format items have been removed to Oversize Materials and noted in the container list.
  - Advertising Hall of Fame certificate, 1984 (Box 11)
  - [America's Awards, Blue Ribbon Selection Committee Appreciation Award, undated: Moved to Oversize Materials, Box 22] (Box 11)
  - Bureau of Advertising award photograph, undated (Box 11)
  - European Heads of Office photograph, 1980 (Box 11)
  - [Elliott 60th birthday, 1981: Removed to Oversize Materials, Box 23] (Box 11)
  - Elliott portrait photographs, undated (Box 11)
  - Elliott Tribute bound program, 1982 (Box 11)
  - Travel
    - Greywalls, 1966 (Box 11)
    - Hong Kong, 1980 (Box 11)
    - Jakarta, 1975 (Box 11)
    - Nairobi, 1978 (Box 11)
    - Rhine, 1966 (Box 11)
  - OBM and associates photographs, 1965 (Box 11)
  - Office photographs, 1974-1975 (Box 11)
  - Retirement celebration, Monaco, 1982 (Box 11)
  - Ronald Reagan
    - Letter, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Photograph, 1988 (Box 11)
  - United States Information Agency Award, 1982 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera, 1966-1986 and undated (Box 11)
  - Three-dimensional items (Box 12)
    - Lifetime Achievement Award, Advertising Educational Foundation, 2003 (Box 12)
    - O&M International Management Meeting, Monaco, Award, 1982 (Box 12)
- Printed Material, 1964-2001 and undated, 3 Boxes
  Contains meeting and event programs; issues of advertising magazines and journals; and newsletters. Includes O&M newsletters Flagbearer and Viewpoint. Also includes two books: 50th Advertising Hall of Fame; and OBM, A Celebration, One Hundred and Twenty-Five Years in Advertising. Includes several items in Spanish from Elliott's 1986 trip to Argentina. Materials arrived loose and in no apparent order. Items were grouped by publishing organization and title, where applicable, and arranged alphabetically.
  - AAAA Annual meeting programs, 1968 (Box 13)
  - Ad Council bulletins, 1975-1990 (Some items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 22) (Box 13)
  - Ad Week, 1999-2001 (Box 13)
  - [Advertising Age, 1980: (Box 13)
  - American Advertising magazine, 1984-1993 (Box 13)
  - Books
    - 50th Advertising Hall of Fame, 1999 (Box 13)
    - OBM, A Celebration, One Hundred and Twenty-Five Years in Advertising, 1975 (Box 13)
  - Flagbearer newsletter, 1960-1994 (Some items removed to Oversize Materials, Box 22) (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Advertising magazines, 1963-1987 (Box 13)
    - Booklets and programs, 1974-1981 (Box 13)
    - Newsletters, 1964-1990 (Box 13)
  - Programs (Box 14)
    - Convention programs, 1979-1987 (Box 14)
    - O&M staff meeting programs, 1979-1985 (Box 14)
    - Special event programs, 1966-1967 (Box 14)
  - Synposis newsletter, 1966-1968 (Box 14)
  - Viewpoint, 1973-1994, 4 folders (Box 14)
- Reports, 1956-1986 and undated, 2 Boxes
  Contains reports prepared for O&M staff meetings and for O&M clients; overseas offices; and the Federal Trade Commission. Includes findings on hiring practices regarding women and minorities in the advertising business, and specifically at O&M. Clients represented include Shell Oil, Du Pont Men's Wear. Also includes a 1975 report on American attitudes towards the idea of Puerto Rico becoming a U.S. state. Original folder titles were maintained, and items were arranged alphabetically.
  - Australia, 1969 (Box 14)
  - Federal Trade Commission, 1983 (Box 14)
  - Japan, 1972 (Box 14)
  - Manila, 1964-1965 (Box 15)
  - Minority groups, 1972-1975, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Ogilvy & Mather
    - Annual reports, 1966-1986 (Box 15)
    - Expansion opportunities, 1969 (Box 15)
  - Progress report on affirmative action, 1968 (Box 15)
  - Report on full-page versus smaller advertisements fo Du Pont Men's Wear, 1956 (Box 15)
  - Shell, 1981 (Box 15)
  - Statehood for Puerto Rico, 1975 (Box 15)
  - Study of Reputation of O&M, 1975 (Box 15)
  - Summary of Pertinent Information about O&M, 1963 (Box 15)
  - Women, 1973 (Box 15)
  - Wunderman, Ricotta & Kline merger, undated (Box 15)
- Stocks, 1964-1989, 1 Box
  Contains correspondence and memoranda relating to O&M's profit-sharing plan; Elliott's company holdings; as well as general notices and reports to O&M shareholders. Items from 1972-1973 arrived in a labeled folder, which was maintained. Two copies of a proposal for the merger of Mather & Crowther arrived in report covers. Report covers were removed, and proposals were placed in folders, with original titles maintained. Folder titled Miscellaneous was derived from materials gathered from unfoldered, loose correspondence, and placed in two folders of miscellaneous stock-related correspondence.
  - General memoranda, 1965-1981, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Merger with Mather and Crowther, 1964, 2 folders (Box 16)
- Writings and Speeches, 1945-2004 and undated, 5 Boxes
  Consists primarily of typewritten speeches written by Jock Elliott for presentation at meetings of O&M; the AAAA; as well as at invited talks at other organizations, clubs, colleges and universities. Includes some speeches written during Elliott's employment at BBDO between 1945 and 1956. Also included are hand- and typewritten drafts and published copies of Elliott's articles written for Cosmopolitan and the New York Times Magazine, of Elliott's two books on Christmas, as well as miscellaneous short writings and poems. Includes Elliott's eulogy for David Ogilvy written for the edited volume Farewell: The Greatest Eulogies of Our Time. The majority of speeches arrived in chronological order, with some appearing interspersed among loose files of other series. Speeches from correspondence, meeting and printed matter series were removed and placed in this series, in chronological order. Elliott's other writings arrived unfoldered and in no apparent order. Where possible, they were foldered and arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Index of speeches (Box 16)
  - BBDO, 1945-1959, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - General, 1962-1969, 6 folders (Box 16)
  - General, 1970-1977, 10 folders (Box 17)
  - General, 1977-1982, 9 folders (Box 18)
  - General, 1982-1997, 12 folders (Box 19)
  - General, 1998-2004, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - A Ha! Christmas, An Exhibition of Jock Elliott's Christmas Books (book), 1999 (Box 20)
  - How Hard It Is to Write Easily, Cosmopolitan magazine, 1981 (Box 20)
  - Institute of Canadian Advertising, Graham Phillips Speech, 1978 (Box 20)
  - Inventing Christmas, How Our Holiday Came to Be (book), 2001 (Box 20)
  - Memories of a Battleship, 1990 (Box 20)
  - New Year's Day poems, 1978-1992 (Box 20)
  - David Ogilvy, in Farewell, The Greatest Eulogies of Our Time, 2003 (Box 20)
  - Perfect Christmas Card, undated (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 20)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1984-1988 and undated, 1 Box
  Contains videos of events, including the 1984 Advertising Hall of Fame luncheon; the 1987 O&M Institute of Directors Annual Conference; and a 1986 WNET broadcast entitled "Gala of Stars." Also includes a New York Times-produced film entitled Iphigene and two short features on the careers of Jock and Eleanor Elliott. Videos were arranged alphabetically, with those produced by O&M grouped together.
  Restrictions on Access: Original videotapes are closed to research until use copies can be made. Contact Research Services for more information.
  - Originals [Closed to research]